#### **INTRODUCTION**

**Towhid Ahmed** is a man with a vision to integrate social development of Bangladesh with business, social initiatives, Artificial Intelligence and technology-based entrepreneurships and knowledge development.

He invests his thoughts, ideas and knowledge and expertise to help the society to become a better place for living.



#### **S**PECIALTIES

Project Management, Training & Facilitation, Digital Marketing, Advertising, Event Management & Activation, Marketing and Management consultancy, Information &

Communication Technology (ICT), Video editing/production, Creative designs.

# **BACKGROUND & PREAMP**

#### **TOWHID AHMED**

is the only son of Rafique Ahamed and one of the grand-sons of Late Bazal Ahmed Swadagar, one of the prominent industrialists of 1960's and a great contributor of Chittagong.

Rafique Ahamed is considered as an eminent personality of port city Chittagong for his

social works, philanthropic initiatives, businesses, social networks, charity and remarkable qualities and public speaking abilities. Throughout his life, he dedicated himself for social causes and development and thus, founded a Non-Government Organization (NGO) named "MAMATA" in 1983. He's the eldest son of Late Bazal Ahmed Swadagar, the proud owner of BANGLADESH RICE MILLS and Industries of the then East Pakistan. Rafique Ahamed received the prestigious **Ekushey Podok** for his outstanding contribution in Socioeconomic Development in Bangladesh.



Mr. Ahamed is also a Life member of Lions Clubs International and became the proud 'District Governor' of Lions Clubs Intl. District 315 -B4 in 2003. He and his organization **MAMATA** is the receiver of thirteen (16) National Awards which includes "Best Social Worker", "Best Organization", "YUNESCO AWARD 1992", "Best Microfinance Institution" Award by Citi Foundation" etc. and many international awards including "Melvin Jones-Fellowship".

Following the roots and paths of father and grand-father, Towhid Ahmed also involved himself in several extra-curricular, social and youth driven activities since his high school period. He was an active member, Executive Committee member, Director and office bearer of LEO Clubs International: District 315-B4, AIESEC (World's largest student organization with exchange program), North South University Social Services Club (NSUSSC), Junior Chamber International (JCI) and Alumni Association of North South University (AANSU).

Towhid Ahmed found his keen interest in Social Business models & Entrepreneurships, Knowledge Sharing, Marketing & Communication since his university period and thus involved himself at several national and global case competitions and merit programs and achieved "Order of Merit" at Global Academic Challenge 2008 organized by Marketing Agencies Associations Worldwide (MAAW). After completing graduation from North South University, he started his career at PR, Communication and Marketing Agencies. He was an active and Organizing Committee member of the "Social Business Forum-2012" and "Social Business Forum 2013" hosted at North South University.

A notable feature of Towhid Ahmed is his connection and involvements with the most prominent public and private universities of Bangladesh including Chittagong University, Institute of Business Administration (IBA), Dhaka University, North South University, Brac University, East West University, American International University-Bangladesh, Premier University, East Delta University, United International University and University of Liberal Arts and Science for Volunteer Development programs, Youth Programs and Training Facilitations.



He trained, facilitated and managed a brilliant pool of volunteers and liaison officers for 11<sup>th</sup> South Asian Games (Formerly known as SAF Games) Dhaka 2010 as a Trainer and Facilitator of 'Volunteer Management Sub-Committee' and also trained and developed volunteers and protocol officers for 1<sup>st</sup> World Marketing Summit 2012 that was held in Dhaka.

In the year 2015, Towhid Ahmed got associated with development sector and joined **MAMATA** as a part of its Core Management Team. MAMATA, very renowned in Bangladesh, is a social and non-government organization committed to socio-economic developments, health care services, poverty alleviation and livelihood improvement of the disadvantaged people of the society.

MAMATA, over the period of 4 decades, has gradually expanded it's activities in multi sectoral socioeconomic development programs including **TB and Malaria** Control Program in Bangladesh, Microfinance, Health Care Services including Maternity and Child health care, Education for underprivileged children and section of the society, ensuring pure drinking water and sanitation, Prevention of HIV/AIDS, Adolescents Health and Agriculture, Livestock & Fisheries, Women Workers Rights, Gender, Human Rights, Child Rights, Improvement of livelihood of Garments/RMG Workers.

In an era where the world needs progressive future generation, Towhid Ahmed believes that children are the foundation of every nation's growth and development aspirations, and must be at the center of any development initiatives including Right to Education and Proper Health-care facilities.

Under the leadership and supervision of Mr. Towhid Ahmed, Mamata currently runs many programs and projects targeting Health care and Education sector. Programs and projects to be mentioned are "Mamata Health Program" and "Mamata Education Program", "Mamata Sishu Surrokkha Kormosuchi", "Shuchala", "Health Care Services Delivery Project (HCSDP- CCPP)" with the objective of empowering underprivileged children by providing education, nutrition, and wellness support.

The Program/Projects are well aligned to the Education Policy, and SDG Goal 4 (Ensure inclusive and equitable quality education and promote lifelong learning opportunities for all). Mamata works with children (6 months – 18 years) living in difficult circumstances, children from poor and marginalized families, disaster-struck and street children, children of RMG workers and children living in remote villages and hard to reach areas.

In 2009, Mamata Bidyalaya was initiated to provide formal education, recreation and safety to the children of garment workers, marginalized and dropout children with the aim of improving the quality of life of children and their future. For 7 years, ECCD activities were being carried out by Mamata with her own funding and with the support of various donor organizations. The parents of these children were reluctant and somewhat depended on Mamata to mainstream their children into formal education taking this into consideration in 2016 Mr. Towhid Ahmed took initiative to impart formal education to children. To ensure that every child has the opportunity to access education especially the marginalized children and the children of RMG workers. Mamata Bidyalaya operates in its own building and this education program is fully funded by Mamata.

In 2020, Mamata Biyalaya was renamed as **Mamata School and College** as the organization aims to expand this school into a college in the near future. Currently more than 500 students are enrolled in the School and the classroom facilities and all the cultural and recreational activities are adhered following the government directives under the overall supervision of Mr. Ahmed.

Mamata had been implementing the "Children are protected from violence" project since June 2013 with the support of Save the Children International. The long-term implementation of the project has played a significant role in ensuring the safety, security and proper development of vulnerable children in four wards of **Chattogram City Coorporation (CCC)**. Mamata has made 4 child-care spaces functional within the community to ensure childrens rights, positive attitude towards children, positive discipline practice, life skills, and ensuring their rights through various awareness sessions, accountability, and training. The project has phased out in December 2021, the project activities were widely accepted by the local community including children, adolescents, parents, teachers, religious leaders and various government stakeholders and the project created expectations among the population due to its effective role in ensuring child protection. Mr. Ahmed vision was to scale up this impact and hence Mamata decided to implement the program titled "Mamata Shishu Surokkha Kormosuchi" and continued the activities with the target audience.

#### **CAREER**

Currently, Towhid Ahmed is serving as a Director of MAMATA, a social and non-government organization committed to socio-economic developments, health care services, poverty alleviation and livelihood improvement of the disadvantaged people of the society.

#### Jul 2018 – Present

#### **Director at MAMATA** (www.mamatabd.org)

Working with a vision of "A Health hazard free and poverty alleviated Bangladesh upholding Basic Human Rights".

- Director of Information, Communication & Technology (ICT) Department.
- Director (Program & Project)
- Supervising and implementing all the projects and programs.
- Working as a core member of the management to ensure growth of the organization.
- Establishing the positive branding of the organization's image and activities.
- Supervising virtual media operations, PR and engagements.

#### Aug 2015 - Jun 2018

#### **Deputy Director at MAMATA** (www.mamatabd.org)

Mamata is a NGO.

Working with a vision of "A Health hazard free and poverty alleviated Bangladesh upholding basic human rights"

- -Heading Information, Communication & Technology (ICT) department.
- -Heading the program unit.
- Supervising virtual media operations, online communication, software management, all other digital platforms.

#### **November 2011 – July 2013**

#### Bangladesh Brand Forum, as In-Charge, Operations. Dhaka

- -Developing strategies for events and activations.
- -Managing outdoor events and activities.
- -Coordinating with the stakeholders.
- -Supervising administrative responsibilities.
- Coordination with suppliers and vendors.

#### Projects handled as the 'Event Manager'

- ② Communication Summit 2011
- World Marketing Summit 2012
- Best Brand Award.
- IFC Cleaner Production Marketing Campaign.

#### May 2011 - August 2011

#### Account Executive at Interspeed Activation Ltd (Dhaka)

Client service and supporting outdoor events as a member of activation team. Also, coordinating with the vendors of related works.

#### August 2010 - November 2010

#### Internship at Concito PR Dhaka

- Working on Singapore Tourism Board's public relations affairs.
- Preparing checklist on news coverage and articles on daily basis.

#### **April 2010 – May 2010**

#### International Conference on Knowledge Globalization 2010 Dhaka

- Worked as one of the organizers from the student body of North South University.
- Served as a team-leader for volunteers during the conference.
- Also, supported the conference as the 'Master of Ceremony' in inauguration and closing ceremonies.

#### January 2010 - February 2010

#### 11th South Asian Games 2010 (Formerly known as SAF GAMES) Dhaka

- Trained, facilitated and managed a brilliant student pool of volunteers and liaison officers.
- Worked as a protocol officer of Indian Sports Minister, Mr. M. S. Gill during the opening ceremony of the games.
- Also, supported as the *Protocol Officers' Coordinator* during the games.

### **August 2008 – October 2008**

#### Student Worker (Coordinator) at

#### Career & Professional Development Services Department, North South University, Dhaka.

- Support to North South University to organize National Career Fair 2008.

#### **September 2007 – Dec 2007**

#### 1st Non-Resident Bangladeshi (NRB) Conference-2007 Dhaka

- Contributed as an organizer to have the conference for the very first time in Bangladesh.
- Support on Public Relations, Media and Volunteers.

#### June 2007 – August 2007

#### National Career Fair 2007 (NSU) - Student Aide to NSU Dhaka

- Support on public relations and media.
- Support on sponsorship management.
- Stall management for invited companies, brands and organizations.
- Volunteers management.

# **ENTREPRENEURSHIPS & SOCIAL INITIATIVES**

#### January 2013 - June 2015

**Promoton Media & Communication (Chittagong)** 

Founder

www.promotonbd.com

Towhid Ahmed founded a marketing & public relations' agency in 2013 "Promoton" to bring values and importance of branding for organizations and companies through providing several services including advertising, public relations, media buying, consultancy, event management etc. as a part of FREELANCING activity.

#### February 2014 – December 2018

CLUB-PRO Café & Ice-cream (Chittagong)

**Founder and Owner** 

Shop# 207, Highway Plaza, 1st Floor, Lalkhan Bazar, Chittagong.

Also, he is the founder of "CLUB-PRO Café & Ice cream", the very 1<sup>st</sup> European Coffee shop at Chattogram to serve authentic coffee, western foods and international ice-creams. The café often hosted free meals for the unprivileged children of the society to add happiness and smiles in their faces and to encourage others to care and support the underprivileged & street children of the society.

#### **EDUCATION**

July 2022

**EMBA from Mastermind Business School, UK** 

June 2005 – December 2010

Bachelors in Business Administration (BBA) with major in Marketing

North South University (NSU)

Dhaka

July 2004

Higher Secondary Certificate (HSC) under Chittagong Education Board.

Chittagong Cantonment Public College.

Chittagong

## **CONFERENCES & SEMINARS**

Towhid Ahmed believes in learning from every object, activity, experience and person. And to pursue that, he often attends seminars and conferences around the globe.

- Digital Marketing Summit 2019 Dhaka
- Global Social Business Summit 2018 Germany
- Retail Congress 2018 Dhaka
- Exposure & Study tour program on Microfinance Development in China 2016 China
- Exposure visit & Study tour program 2016 Vietnam
- Leadership Summit 2015 Dhaka
- June 2013 Social Business Day 2013 Dhaka
- June 2012 Social Business Day 2012 Dhaka
- World Marketing Summit 2012 Dhaka
- Communication Summit 2011 Dhaka
- International Conference on Knowledge Globalization- 2010 Dhaka
- National Leadership Development Seminar 2009 Sylhet
- Lions Clubs International Convention 2008 Thailand
- March 2008 AIESEC- Asia Pacific eXchange and Leadership Development Seminar (APXLDS) **Japan**
- June 2006 AIESEC- National Leadership Development Seminar Manikgoni
- September 2005 AIESEC- National Leadership Development Seminar Sylhet
- January 2004 International LEO Youth Camp Cox'sBazar

# **AWARDS, ATTACHMENTS & ACHIEVEMENTS**

#### November 2021 - Present

Founding President, Lions Club of Chattogram Ambassador. Lions Clubs International; District 315- B4, Bangladesh

#### Feb 2015 – January 2016

Director, Junior Chamber International (JCI) Chittagong Cosmopolitan

#### Feb 2015 - Present

Director, Alumni Association of North South University (AANSU) Bangladesh

#### December 2009 - Feb 2010

#### 11th South Asian Games 2010 (Formerly known as SAF GAMES) Bangladesh

Trained and managed the 50 member Protocol Officers team to provide hospitality to the international dignitaries of South Asian Games 2010, Dhaka.

#### September 2008 - May 2009

#### National Support Team-Expansion, AIESEC International, Dhaka

Responsible for expanding AIESEC locally. I had to select, evaluate and determine possible universities that could be added to AIESEC network as per the AIESEC International rules and systems.

#### May 2008 – July 2008

#### Intellectual & Integrated Marketing Strategy Team [MSTi2] Dhaka

Led the five-member team naming 'MSTi2' from North South University which secured the 'Órder of Merit' certificate in the MAA Academic Challenge-2008 organized by *Marketing Agencies Association Worldwide (MAAW)*.

#### May 2007 - April 2008

Vice President, Department of Communication – AIESEC in North South University Dhaka

Facilitation/management of the common vision and associated initiatives that allowed the chapter to increase its performance. Leading a team of 50 dynamic members to activate leadership through social impact. Core responsibility was to manage the department of communication.

#### April 2004- March 2005

# 2nd Vice President -- LEO Club Of CTG MAMATA (LEO CLUBS INTERNATIONAL DISTRICT-315-B4) Chittagong

Had been providing important suggestions and decisions for the SOCIAL WORKS of LEO clubs which are specially- Blood donation, Blood grouping, Eye-test campaign, Tree plantation.

#### April 2003- March 2004

Treasurer -- LEO Club Of CTG MAMATA (LEO CLUBS INTERNATIONAL DISTRICT-315-B4) Chittagong

Had control over the whole financial transactions of the club and had to collect the club dues from the members

and the directors.













Toding enterpretations of criticagong share views with the representatives of Crange come of the Dutch Ministry of Pereigin Affairs on the possibilities, obstacles, and ways to over come to create entrepreneurship at the auditorium of Software Technology Park in Agrabat on Tuesday, November 23, 2021. Photo: Courtesy

# Round table discussion Ctg young entrepreneurs, Dutch Ministry delegate share views

PV Desk
A round table meeting was held on 21st November to exchange experiences of young entrepreneurs of Chittagong with the representatives of Orange corner of the Dutch Ministry of Foreign Affairs on the possibilities, obstacles, and ways to overcome to create entrepreneurship. The meeting was held at the auditorium of Software Technology Park in Agrabad of Chattogram city. The participants discussed various aspects of a mature entrepreneurship all ecosystem. During the meeting, Theodore Klouvas, Program Manager of Orange Corners-Netherlands, emphasized strengthening the business infrastructure, creating entrepreneur-friendly institutional learning, and creating a supportive environment for entrepreneurs. Mike Sips, Advisor to the Orange Corners Innovation Fund, and Bas Blaauw, First Secretary for Economic Affairsof Nederland embassy , Mahijabeen | Juader, Senior Advisor, Economic Affairsof Mederland embassy , Mahijabeen | Senior Advisor, Economic and Commercial, Khalid Hasan, Training | Management Specialist, Bangladesh Hi-Tech Park Authority Chvitagong spoke at the open discussions. | Doung entrepreneurs Azizur Rahman Khan, Wasfi Tamim, Bortharul Hasan Chowdhury, Hasnath Mohammed Abu Ubaida, Tahsin Junaid, Mashurur Ahmed, Nazmus Shakib, Arafatul Islam Akib CEO of Startup Chittagong were present at the discussion among others.